from the waiting room. As always, it
does take a minute or so for everybody
in the waiting room to join on in. Um,
but while that is happening, I'll
continue with the introductions. Good
morning, everybody. Uh, I'm Dominic
Zerlo with the New Mexico Department of
Health and I'm the director for the
Center for Medical Cannabis and
Psilocybin. Welcome on this uh,
wonderful Monday morning everyone to the
patient qualification and safety
committee meeting. Uh the chair is Ian
Dunn. And just as a reminder to
everyone, um because we do record these
meetings and we post them up on our
website, um please remember to keep your
language appropriate for all ages and we
definitely appreciate that because
otherwise it delays us when we have to
go in and bleep items. Um so, uh we do
appreciate the assistance on that. And
with that, I will go ahead and turn it
on over to the chair, Ian. Uh, it is
your meeting. Thank you.
>> Good morning everyone. Hi, my name is
Ian Dunn, chair of the patient
qualification and safety committee. Just
wanted to thank you all for being here
today. Um, so we had originally talked
about uh new qualifying conditions uh
going to be adopted after um program
initial implementation. We have not
received any new um evidence that we had
requested from the committee at this
time. So what we are going to use this
time to discuss instead is kind of give
a forum for um public comment on board
actions and board decisions. Um as well
as any questions, comments, concerns
that uh may arise around medical
psilocybin. Um
but at this time if you would like to
participate please introduce yourselves
just your name um any relevant area of
expertise and um any associations you
have. Thank you.
and then Gregory
[clears throat] uh just because it's
easier typing. Gregory Evans um I was
just thinking about this this morning.
So this is are we in dosage?
>> We are in patient qualification safety.
Um dosage is tomorrow right? Yeah. um
related to dosage. I I'm specifically
uh
have a lot of information about the
science behind dosage and how much
we
measure inside a biomass and how to
apply that to um therapeutic settings.
I'm associated with a company called
Ignite Synergy. We make integration
software
[snorts] and I live in Santa Fe.
Thank you. Um, just to point out who has
been in the chat, Sky Rivers, uh, Santa
Fe, Santa Fe reporter covering the
legalization of medical psilocybin. Uh,
Khawk, good morning Khawk Santa Fe. Uh,
Don Moser, hi. uh from Las Vegas, New
Mexico. Perfect. Um so again, this is
going to be general topic. So if anyone
has anything that they would like to
bring up, questions, comments, concerns,
um while I don't think it would be fair
to anyone who was interested in dosage
to like adopt anything or or um kind of
do anything like that, if you do have
something you would like to discuss, uh
we can do that at this time.
Just know it would be preliminary.
and then Kate.
Hi everyone. Yeah. Um going back to the
qualifications and the discussion in the
past about what would be required to add
new qualifying conditions. Um just want
to make sure we have at some point more
of a discussion about what is realistic.
Um there's just not that much
like standard placeboc controlled random
controlled trial um studies but there
are some relevant studies. So I'm just
um you know assuming and hoping sometime
we'll have a discussion about what is a
realistic standard. I've had discussions
with colleagues in various places about
this and you know there's um it dealing
with psychedelics it's not just you know
the usual kind of studies that you could
do with other drugs
just wanted to mention that
and uh while I have
>> anyway um so while I have the microphone
uh also I think some of the recent
unsettledness has been uh I'll just come
out and say you know I'm on the training
and education committee but other
committees felt like seemed like they
were very organized and they had
something to present to the board and
our committee um really didn't uh so you
know do kind of just took on the job
because it needed to move ahead and uh
this week in preparation for the
training and education committee and the
full advisory board meeting. We are
looking at you know organizing our
thoughts taking what's been presented
what's has different viewpoints and um
and hopefully we will have something
more organized
uh in the area of of you know training
and education. So anybody who's
participating in that I know that like
Gregory made a a nice organized uh
system where people can have input. So
just want to mention that u I hope there
will be clarity out of all the con all
the uh discussions and that things will
be uh clear enough to move ahead. Thank
you.
>> Thank you. And yeah, um I really enjoy
that we took the time to reempower that
committee to finish um you know their
work. We largely agreed with a lot of
what the department of health had
proposed um most of it being very
standard um run-of-the-mill stuff. It
was just those few areas. So um as soon
as you know that can be resolved you
know everyone is going to have a
slightly different
favorite flavor of training and
education in terms of quantity and and
system. So trying to find a balance is
is a difficult thing. Um so thank you
guys for taking on that work.
>> Yeah I I get it. there's room for
different opinions and at least we can
have a rationale for well something we
can agree on enough to move ahead. Thank
you [snorts]
>> Brenda Burkart.
Yes, I just wanted to thank Kate for for
that comment and you Ian. Uh yes, um
it's been pretty cut and dry uh from the
beginning, you know, uh trying to
uh get all the competencies
uh there and posted in a document. Uh
because training and education has a lot
to do with um the nitty-gritty of uh
what will be taught, what the training
is going to be like, what what uh right
now we're discussing
uh what the practicum hours are going to
be and the didactic. I think we're
trying to um understand what would be
the best thing, best hours uh to be in
that. But it's a lot more than just uh
training and education. It's all of the
other working parts from the other
committees coming in and contributing to
the education part because there is a
lot to this. Uh, and you know, there's
there's other things that kind of came
up in education and training that um
were um missing parts, but I think we're
getting there now to discuss uh what
these topics need to be addressed and
formulated into a
uh formula of education and training.
So, you know, I want to thank everybody
for coming to those meetings and, uh,
thank you again, Kate, for your
contribution. Um, uh, we're trying to
get together some questions, uh, that
are kind of knocking at the door here
for training and education and, uh, what
that's going to look like, uh, as we
shape, um, what we need to do as far as,
um, uh, reciprocity goes and, uh, the
other formal training that goes into it.
So um you know I want to thank everybody
out there for you know uh coming to
these meetings and um giving their um
you know their advice, their experience
uh you know their knowledge to help
create this program. So I just wanted to
say that thank you.
>> Yes, thank you guys so much. Um, having
some experience in uh, school district
policy,
it it's hard to tell people how to teach
without a becoming overbearing and then
b
without surrendering some level of
realism. It is a genuinely difficult
task. Um, so I I appreciate all of the
work. Um, Gregory
Hey, I don't know if I missed an agenda
or anything today, but
sounds like a conversation.
[laughter]
Um, yeah, like where where are we? Do we
have an agenda?
>> Um, so our original agenda was going to
be any new qualifying conditions, but we
didn't receive any submitted, so it's
just an open forum.
>> Oh, interesting.
in the racy group, we've been pitching
around like things to study in that
capacity. I could pull up a list or
whatever, but [sighs and gasps]
um I think we would all benefit based on
recent experience
um from just going back to the drawing
board, clearing the whiteboard, writing
down our mission, identifying the rules
that the responsibility of this
committee,
reviewing what those look like. um from
the rules version even like just as a
list of numbers with titles, right?
[clears throat] And then going back and
making making sure working it back to
say, "Hey, cool." Because we have
written a lot of recommendation down.
And this committee may not have as much
like rule writing as some of the other
committees, but let's figure out when we
need what ready,
what that is,
so that we don't end up in a situation
where
rules that we could have influenced
uh end up kind of just surprising us.
whatever that looks like.
That is all.
Thank you
and Denali.
Good morning. Um, sorry I was a little
bit late. So grateful for the rundown of
what we're doing right now. Um, and
maybe this has been expressed by others.
I just want to say I think uh it's a it
should be a priority to see major
depressive disorder added um in addition
to treatment [clears throat] resistant
depression. I don't know that it's fair
nor was the intent um [clears throat]
in including treatment resistant
depression but not major depressive
disorder to require that somebody you
know go through at least two courses of
um of protocols on their depression to
to qualify. So that feels like a major
priority and I know there are many other
conditions that would benefit but I hope
that we can come to a consensus about
that being um being a priority to add
Yes. So in our second round of
qualifying conditions that this
committee has approved um so once the
program is implemented then
uh the board will review this
committee's um recommendations which
include major depressive disorder. I
agree that someone should not have to
fail to some in some cases less
effective options before um being given
the medicine that works for them. So um
I completely agree with that point.
Thank you.
and Gregory,
do we have anybody talking about dosage
and protocols for different conditions
or is the stance of the program blast
everybody to outer space and hope they
come back?
So we have not developed specific
guidance for dosing of um like specific
conditions. Um our general
guideline is that the psychedelic
therapist would have dosage authority um
to you know weigh the costs and benefits
of different things. So like for
instance um SSRIs tend to blunt
uh the effects of psychedelics. So they
may need a higher dose or um you know
different things like that need to be
taken into account. So we haven't
generated that guidance yet.
>> Sure. But I mean we have like
um a lot of experts but even in the
field of experts we have like
a lot of understanding about how to
utilize psilocybin for
getting people over the hump, right?
Like we always want to make sure that
people get enough, right? And whatever
that means. But like [clears throat]
what if
a you know somebody who's suffering from
PTSD from sexual trauma just needs to
sit in a room and talk. Is there like
are there people talking about like how
to use lower doses or is like there
is anyone talking about anything besides
25 30 milligrams? Like do we have like
is there any guidance? Is there any
conversation? Is there like do people
realize that we don't have to use that
much to get effects
depending on what effects like and then
like this this rolls into like um pain
treatment and and other conditions that
we might be considering whereas like
major depressive disorder
[clears throat] I'm a huge fan someone
who is not me may
recommend somebody with major depressive
disorder to take you
3 to four milligrams of psilocybin
equivalency every day with their
vitamins in the morning. That's not like
in the structure of what is allowed
inside this program, but we can still
have those conversations about protocol
and guidance and potential research um
that exist. So we can build framework
for um
expanding the scope of our practice so
to speak.
Okay. Yeah. And we can definitely talk
about um like our guidance ranges
um especially for certain conditions. I
know PTSD is one of those that is um at
high risk of causing psychological
disturbance um if performed incorrectly.
So um for instance like
sending them to outer space as you said
or um you know just not providing
adequate therapeutic care. So definitely
we would want to explore some of those
lower dose options to cuz you can always
give them more you can't give them less.
I mean there's a hump there's like in
dosage there is like there's like access
to peak right and sometime like a lot of
therapists do in the world of practice
today very into updosing it's not my
that's not not my preference I would
rather put somebody directly where where
the target is right
that's just me and I'm not a therapist
but um but you mentioned the container
of care right so like the therapeutic
practice ice is very much what prevents
a lot of that like damage in that
container, right?
But I really look forward to when we get
to discuss like how to bring people up
into that safe zone as opposed to like
ride in a you know and also there's
different types of PTSD
you know I think there's a line of
people ready to talk about different
kinds of PTSD
>> and then Brenda
>> um one thing I've noticed that uh yeah
the qualifying conditions that um not a
whole lot has been talked about uh
addiction here. Um
my background is addiction and uh what
would be the qualifying
uh what would qualify uh someone with
addiction like okay so for instance
uh they would definitely have to be
cleaned for um some time uh off of their
uh drug of choice. Um the other thing is
is that um there is still a lot of
stigma surrounding addiction that you
know my experience working with patients
is that a lot of them don't want to use
any medication whatsoever and that this
would be their their last hope. But I
don't think that the
um what has been in a lot of rehabs and
this sort of thing, how would that
uh how would we be treating uh people
with addiction with with psilocybin? Um
it seems like to me that
um especially people who have a very
high tolerance to
um many drugs and and alcohol when
they've been clean for a while um how
would they you know go to a clinic and
and get treated for that when um the
majority of uh people like myself um
even though I you know have experience
with lucinogenics
that uh how would that
how would that be taught uh for using um
uh helping people with substance use
because it it there there seems to be
like this very hard line of abstinence
and so trying to get over that hurdle or
that stigma
um is going to be I think a really big
one um and in and treating people with
addiction. Um I I would just like to
know what people's uh views on that
would be.
>> Yeah. And um I think to when we consider
addiction, we have to consider that
there are many um
I don't want to say stages, but there
are many levels to how
far the disease has progressed.
And so
when like someone with um nicotine use
disorder is not going to have the same
um lifec crushing effects as someone
with you know very severe um opiate
dependency or empetamine dependency. Um
but again that may be my own implicit
biases that are affecting this
conversation. So I do think we do need
to take some extra time to consider how
we are going to help those patients.
Uh K.
>> Oh, sorry.
>> Sorry. Um I I just wanted to add that um
uh the training uh for like clinicians
uh in addiction um is very very
systematic
you know uh someone comes in with you
know u alcohol for instance and so
there's a a lot of didactic that goes
into the psychoeducation part of you
know addiction.
Um
yeah, I'm just I'm just wondering uh how
to integrate,
you know, the training and and all of
that. I guess it would be any just like
any other training uh for clinicians in
in that regard, but um people with
addiction would have to definitely take
UAS before they even, you know, uh the
day of um getting treatment with
psilocybin. So, you know, I'm thinking
about a lot of different things when it
comes to substance use and um
uh how people can be um how this can be
integrated into the addiction program.
>> Thank you. And Kate,
>> yeah, I'm glad Brenda brought that up.
is, you know, there's an end of life
care committee, but there aren't any
groups uh that I'm aware of specifically
working on the other qualifying
conditions. And maybe they don't need
their own committees. Maybe, you know,
if this committee has enough bandwidth,
you know, that could be helpful to take
a look at what um you know, what might
apply to the other particular
conditions. So my my background I mean I
was a certified trauma specialist back
in the 90s and that's really my um
particular area of focus and I think it
would deserve some thought about
you know who is really qualified to deal
with PTSD or like addictions because
it's its own specialty. Um so where do
you think that you know those
considerations fit in our overall scheme
here?
Um so
I
don't believe that we can
basically
partition out any
group. So for instance the regulations
that apply even to end of life um or
apply to all the conditions apply to end
of life. The reason they got special
consideration
and honestly was in my mind the other
three were psychiatric conditions
whereas end of life is an psychiatric
plus a medical condition and so that's
why they were not in the same group. But
overall when we finish up the
regulations each person has to be
treated the same under the law. So we
can look at substance use disorder and
trauma therapy but I can't say if you
have substance use disorder you can only
go to uh a substance use disorder
specialist. So what we could do though
or what can happen is patients who are
are searching for um
a a psilocybin therapist. If you already
have um you know you're an addiction
specialist, then that doesn't go away
because you're working within the
psilocybin um program. You still are an
addiction specialist and that should be
a calling card to your specific practice
if that applied. Um,
but I hope that helps.
>> Well, you know, it's it's good to have
some conversation around this. I mean,
the fact that there are addiction
specialists, I think, is relevant where,
you know, in the end of life care, we're
coming up with a specialized training
that we want people to have. So, it's
not just anybody. And it's, you know,
it's it's a very small and reasonable
training compared to what people go
through to be addiction specialists or
any other kind of therapist. But I guess
um you know, maybe there's nothing
officially that will be required for
people to work with substance abuse, but
at least
um I know I'm thinking of what could we
have available even if it's not a
minimum requirement. what could we have
available in that area of working with
addictions with psilocybin because you
know there's some specialized things to
know about it that most people don't
know.
>> Yeah. And I think something that we
could potentially do is um kind of like
how nursing works. So there are all or
this is going to be an overgeneralized
statement but all RNs can work wherever
an RN is but if you want you know
to show that you are dedicated to a
field you can become a PM and um a
critical care nurse uh and there are
different certifications. So it could be
something like that where we will allow
you if you want to to not work with a
substance use professional but we can
provide a um end of life or substance
abuse
certification to say this person is they
specialize in it if that makes sense.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Good. Thank you.
>> Thank you James.
Morning Ian everyone. Uh I just wanted
to get your thoughts Ian on going back
to Gregory's uh followup on dosing. You
know there's a lot of thoughts on you
know single dose versus multiple dose in
a session. You know there's a like uh
what's your thoughts on that as far as
you know are you thinking if the
therapist or is that up to the
therapist? And if it is, you know, um,
you know, just thoughts, right? I'm just
throwing stuff out here like, you know,
the therapist says, "Hey, no, they're a
single dose type of person or they're
multiple dose, you know, where you get
that failure to launch and they're
allowed to at that point then redose."
Just thoughts because we need to think
about that stuff uh because that goes
down to the safety thing. Um, and the
various conditions of course will affect
those single versus multiple dose during
that one session. you know, will that
require the patient to come back, which
is fine. You know, they can come back or
or, you know, do they need something to
get that launch point more activated?
Um, just thoughts. And then the other
thing here is group versus individual
because a lot of these things are going
to fall into dosing and with the groups
and then individually and then if you're
going to allow them to multiple dose in
a group versus just single dose in
groups. And so just thing throwing you
know those thoughts out there for the
group and and there's literature out
there but there's also just just wanted
to get your opinion on stuff. Thank you
so much.
>> Yeah. So I um so in a perfect world I
would love if everyone we already knew
their gut biome and we could say here is
the dose that will work for you. Um but
unfortunately everyone's gut biome is
different. People process psilocybin and
psilocin differently. So, I would
personally leave it up to therapist's
discretion. If you are a therapist and
you have a lot of experience in
psychedelics, I don't doubt that you
might be able to
dose better than someone who's new. Um,
but if there is someone and they say,
"Oh, we gave them this, we waited
per protocol x number of hours. Um, we
are allowing a redose that starts over
their transportation timer, but um, it
would still I would still allow it as
long as the facilitator recognized that
that timer that 12 hours reset.
So that amount of time where we have to
they can't drive where um, they are in
an altered state, we have to just be
aware of that. Um, if you are a
psychedelic therapist,
Gregory
pharmacological um
[cough and clears throat]
pharmacologically are you considering
ROA in that timer?
I I need a Can you help me? What's ROA?
>> Root of administration.
How does it get into your body?
>> What form? What preparation?
>> Okay. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> What part of your body does it go into
>> in
is there any outside of
oral consumption? Is there any
methodology that is currently used in
psilocybin medicines?
>> Well, yes. We're there's no injectables.
Um, but there are other parts of the
body that you can ingest through.
Um, I'm [clears throat] not teaching a
class in in that today, but like there's
preparations. Is it made into tea? Is it
extracted with citrus? and taken as
lemon tech. Is it pro is it made into
chocolate? Are you chewing it and
swallowing it? Are you chewing it and
keeping it in your lip?
All roots of administration
affect your halflife. How soon the
chemical converts in your system,
crosses your brain barrier. Like I'm not
saying like you have the the barrier set
way out. We're fine. There's no risk.
But I mean it's like if you take if you
do lemon tech your client should be good
to drive in like eight hours not 12
>> right and [clears throat]
um
that that makes sense but
>> I think I'm not trying to argue
wondering if we've considered considered
how things are consumed in our in our
conversation about
>> honestly in my
>> if I don't know I can't speak for anyone
who else has spoken in these committees
I have not considered other like I
hadn't considered lemonche which is
I should have that's the how you make
I'm here to ask the question
[laughter]
>> but
um no that is a very good point because
there are several methods and even
looking at um there are several methods
I'm I don't want to say the word out
loud but Gregory you know what I'm
talking
Um Brenda,
>> suppository is the clinical term.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Um I guess um this could also be part of
uh education too is like um what would
the patient prefer? Um like Leech,
>> what is the patient what is the patient
aware of?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Absolutely. like it as you
said like Levantech is you know it's um
uh
yeah uh the shorter uh acting um from
what I know it's a little bit more uh
intense
uh tea for instance uh could be another
you know and when you're sipping tea
that's going to take a little time you
know tech it's a shot you know type of
thing um uh uh a suppository that could
take a a quite a while. Um you know uh
maybe you know maybe we need to um uh
you know find out what you know some of
the research is on on that. Uh but I um
think that leaving it up to the uh
patient or the client um and educating
them on what their uh preference is uh
you know even though it's going to be
mostly their first time but I think
education is probably what they need
about how to uh how they want to take
it. And if our educators aren't aware of
the pantheon of administration routes,
then how are they going to teach the
people who are providing services?
>> Absolutely. Yeah.
>> So, we just need I mean, and by the way,
like I'm not an advocate of any
particular specific way of things. Like
that's not the point here. The point is
like literal like textbook getting
everything on paper so that like all of
the science is forward and available
and just how
how you want
>> theoretically um cuz now now you have me
thinking about it because I knew about
dissolving for those that don't know
lemonche is just dissolving um
psilocybin mushrooms in lemon juice um
which basically mimics the
digestion process and so it converts
that psilocybin into psilicin
um it makes it stronger and faster
and that might be a feasible solution.
Not saying again this probably can't be
rule but it could be guidance that if
someone is you know driving out of town
for a session and they need to get out
like we could try doing that because it
gives larger quantities of psilicin
which has a shorter halflife.
I also saw Lisa's hand up at one point,
but I don't know if you still had a
comment.
Can I address Skye's question?
>> Yes. Sorry, I hadn't had the chat open.
>> That's okay. I do want to say for clar
just for just so it's on the record,
Leech does not make anything stronger.
Um, it doesn't make it more powerful. it
like I could draw on a graph how how it
works but like it just
it's a citrus extraction that that
begins the conversion process to solosin
as you said but it doesn't change if you
have you know 10 milligrams of solosin
equivalent it's going to be 10 milligs
of solosin equivalent it's just going to
arrive more quickly be more consistent
and and subside in an even manner
instead of up and down. Whereas
psilocybin while it converts in your
body creates peaks and valleys and goes
on for much longer.
>> Yes, you are absolutely correct. Um I
meant like not that it becomes stronger
that it
>> already is processed like it's it's
started
>> but
>> it can be jolting if you're not prepared
for it. Um, so with Sky, the the the
conditions that I put up above that were
adopted May 4th in this committee were
the conditions that we were going to
consider moving into next year to begin
talking about. It's not that any of
these are
in progress. These are uh conditions
that are I don't know somebody with
words uh up for consideration.
Is that not sure
I don't you of all people I do not want
to um provide information that is not
absolutely correct.
All right. Does anyone else have
anything they would like to share?
And also sorry to respond to Sky Rivers.
So she had said um in summary what is
preventing this um qualifying list
becoming broad enough that this is
effectively an open access psilocybin
therapy in all but name. And so I would
cite the actual medical psilocybin act
which gave us not only the authority to
recognize qualifying conditions but to
recognize qualifying symptom clusters.
And so it's not that it is an open
access policy. it is that there is
a huge tremendous amount of impact of
trauma on on or psilocybin on the impact
of trauma on our brains and so I think
that they can provide a lot of relief
from those existing conditions. Um,
Dominic,
>> good morning everybody and thank you. I
just really wanted to expand on that
that question from Sky. And so part of
it, Sky, is this committee sort of uh
brings those topics on up, makes the
initial recommendation to the board,
then the board will actually need to
review those recommendations for the
addition of other committee or other
qualifications.
um those recommendations, if the board
does recommend a new condition be added,
it then goes to the secretary of health
and then the secretary of health would
have the final um the final decision
with regard to that. Um so this isn't a
a quick program um process. This is
something that does have multiple layers
of looking at it and seeing what is
potential, you know, potentially there
as far as evidence. you know, Kate
mentioned earlier about ensuring that
there is enough evidence and appropriate
evidence. And so that's a part of what
is reviewed at those different levels.
And so, um, just wanted to clarify, it's
not just something that happens in this
committee. If this committee does
approve it, that means it goes to the
board. If the board approves it as a
recommendation, then it goes to the
department. And so, very similar. I know
many people are familiar with that same
process with regard to medical cannabis.
there have been many conditions while
some are approved there are many
conditions that also are not approved.
So many more get submitted than um you
know than just those that are approved.
So I hope that that that helps um with
regard to the process.
So thank you
All righty. Well, if there are is no
additional discussion,
why don't we push this next meeting to
give people more time to review evidence
um for qualifying conditions um and to
just kind of prepare as well as give the
department some time to finish those
training and education rules. Why don't
we push to Monday, October 5th at 9:00
a.m.?
>> Uh, that works on this side of the
department. Ian
>> Perfect.
All righty. Um, well, thank you all so
much for coming, sharing your viewpoints
with us. I really, it really has been a
thoughtprovoking exercise. So, I might
need to start doing this more often. Um,
but thank you all so much for showing
up. It is so much easier to not show up
to things than it is to show up. So, I
appreciate every single one of you and
every single one of you that shows up,
not just to this these meetings, but to
the board and to all the other
committees and to all of those things.
You guys help make the process go along
and I appreciate you from the bottom of
my heart. Thank you everyone and have a
wonderful Monday.
>> And on behalf of the department, I echo
those sentiments. Thank you everybody.
It's these conversations that really
help us to make this program to be a
successful one. So thank you everybody.
Hope you all have a great week.